Samuel Whittemore Boggs Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Samuel Whittemore Boggs Papers 1912-1954
MSS13094
Boggs, Samuel Whittemore, 1889-1954
7,000 items
31 containers plus 1 oversize
29 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Geographer, inventor, and cartographer. Correspondence, writings, subject files, research data, printed matter, and other material relating mainly to Boggs's geographic studies and to his inventions and research interests.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Boggs, Samuel Whittemore, 1889-1954.
Subjects
Boundaries.; Cartography--Instruments.; Cartography.; Geography.; International relations.; Map projection.; Maps.; Missions.; Regionalism.; Traffic signs and signals.; Water boundaries.
Occupations
Authors.; Cartographers.; Geographers.; Inventors.
Provenance
The papers of Samuel Whittemore Boggs, geographer, inventor and cartographer, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife in 1955, with an additional gift of Dorothy C. Novak, professional associate of Boggs, in 1967.
Additional Guides
A note on these papers appeared in the Library of Congress Information Bulletin (April 30, 1956).
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Samuel Boggs are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1899, 2 Mar. Born, Coolidge, Kans.
1909 B.L., Berea College, Berea, Ky.
1909 1912 Private secretary to president, Berea College, Berea, Ky.
1912 1913 Student, Yale Divinity School, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1913 1914 Secretarial work, Union Pacific Railroad, Omaha, Neb.
1914 1919 Secretarial and executive work for International Committee of YMCA and other organizations, New York
1916 Married Amy Burt Bridgeman
1916 1924 Geographical research, map compilation, editor, American Book Co., including maps for World Missionary Atlas, 1921-1924
1924 M.A. in geography, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1924 1954 Geographer, Department of State
1939 1942 Lecturer, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1945 1946 Lecturer, American University, Washington, D.C.
1954 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Samuel Whittemore Boggs (1889-1954) span the years 1912-1954. Consisting of correspondence, drafts of articles, notes, maps, printed matter, and clippings, the collection focuses on Boggs's diverse geographical interests. Included are files of geographic data on various regions of the world, reports of missionary activity, material relating to Boggs's mapping inventions, files for proposed studies, and preparatory materials for his lectures, speeches, and publications. The collection is organized into seven series: Correspondence, Professional File, Writings File, Lectures, Subject File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
Topics of significance include boundary delimitation, regionalism, global relations, and water boundaries. Featured are Boggs's pioneering work as inventor of an eumorphic equal-area map projection, graphic traffic signals, and a universal graphic charting instrument. Also in the papers are notes on courses given at Columbia University.
Boggs's filing system was retained in parts of the collection, including a "Regions of the World" section in the Subject File series. A guide to the section is in the first folder of the material.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Correspondence, 1916-1954
Professional File, 1927-1953
Writings File, 1931-1954
Lectures, 1938-1942
Subject File, 1915-1954
Miscellany, 1912-1945
Oversize, 1932
Container List
- Correspondence, 1916-1954 (Box 1-2)
  Special correspondence of letters to and from Boggs as geographer with the State Department and general correspondence.
  Arranged alphabetically within the two groups.
  - Special Correspondence, State Department (Box 1)
    - “A-B” miscellaneous
    - “C” miscellaneous
    - “D-G” miscellaneous
    - “H” miscellaneous
    - “J-L” miscellaneous
    - Library of Congress
    - “M-P” miscellaneous
    - “R-S” miscellaneous
    - “T-Z” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - “A-B” miscellaneous
    - Beach, Harlan P.
    - “C-E” miscellaneous
    - “F-G” miscellaneous
    - “H-J” miscellaneous
    - “K-P” miscellaneous
    - “R-S” miscellaneous
    - St. John, Burton
    - “T-W” miscellaneous
    - Washburn, H. M.
    - “Z” miscellaneous
- Professional File, 1927-1953 (Box 3-18)
  Material related to professional projects during the various phases of Boggs's career.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Association of American Geographers (Box 3)
  - "An Atlas of Ignorance"
    - American Philosophical Society, Paper
    - Cost Estimates, Project
    - Ford Foundation, Project
    - Forward, Introduction, Project
    - Manuscripts, Initial Drafts
    - Map Illustrations (Lantern Slices), Paper
    - Map Plans, Project
    - Maps Under Wenner-Gren Grant
    - Miscellany, Project
    - Newspaper Clippings & Radio, Paper
    - Notes for Text, etc., Project
    - Other Correspondence, Paper
    - Outline (Subjects, etc.), Project
    - Plan for Atlas, Project
    - Search for Support (except the American Philosophical Society), Project
    - State Department, Paper
  - Aviation Maps, Drafting Companies, 1928-1929
  - Cartographic Instruments and Patents (Box 4)
    - Universal Graphic Charting Instrument
      - Correspondence, 1932-1939
      - Application for Patents
      - Application for Registration of Trade-Mark
      - Map Projection Application Papers
      - Orders for Drafting Instrument
      - Advertising
      - Contract Draft
      - Description and Instructions
      - Related Instruments and Ideas
      - General, (2 folders); (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - The Classification and Cataloging of Maps and Atlases
    - Requests for Manual Refused, (3 folders)
    - Requests for Loan of Manual to be Granted (Box 7)
    - Requests for Reproductions
    - Manual
      - Accomplishments, Analytics, Facsimiles, Citations
      - Area Headings
      - Atlases, Cataloging
      - Bibliography
      - Catalog
        - Entries
        - Examples
        - Rules, etc.
      - Classification, Theory, etc.
      - Consolidation of Book and Map Catalog
      - Definitions
      - Exploring Expeditions, Cataloging
      - Index
      - Subject Headings
    - Photostat Sheets, Cards Selected from American Geographical Society Research, Catalog for Department of State and Office of the Coordinator, Nov. 1941
    - Area Classification, Liberia
    - Subject Classification
    - Subject Headings, Old Material (Box 8)
    - Manual, with Annotations and Corrections, 1945
    - Area Classification, Current, 1937-1945
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1940-1951
    - Classification and Cataloging of Maps in Other Collections
    - Projections, Small Illustrations Used in Identification Tables
    - Prime Meridians (Box 9)
    - "Master Catalog" in GE [Department of State, Office of the Geographer]
    - Map Cataloging in Other Libraries
      - 1924-1929
      - Post 1930
    - Map Scales, used in earlier centuries, chiefly
    - Lists of Packages [as packed by donor]
    - Association of American Geographers
      - Committee Report
        - 30 Dec. 1936
        - Related Material
    - Manual Gifts, Letters and Replies, 1932
    - Map Manual (Box 10)
      - Requests, Current, 1934-1941
      - Correspondence re Publishing, 1932-1943
    - Conferences with Library of Congress, Division of Maps, 1931-1936
    - American Library Association Map Catalog Code Revision, 1939
    - Exhibit of American Library Association Technique, Experimental Cards Arranged by Author, by Area, 1939
    - Experimental Material, Data from Maps, circa 1930-1931
    - Map Cataloging
      - General
      - Classed Catalog
      - Developments in Department of State, before 1930
    - Map Manual
      - Archives
      - General Correspondence, 1932-1945 (Box 11)
      - Samuel Whittemore Boggs, Material
      - Loans, 1932-1945
      - Preface and Introduction
      - Definitions
        - Material to Be Used
        - Old Material
      - Map Projections, Appendix K
      - Map Scale
    - Subject Classification (Box 12)
    - Subject Index
    - Classification and Notation, Old Material
    - Manual
      - Copy Sent to Press, 1945
      - Carbons of Material Sent to Miss Cole, 1945
      - SLA Correspondence re Publishing, etc., 1944-1945 (Box 13)
    - Errata and Revisions
      - Printed, Oct.-Nov. 1945 [?]
      - Mimeographed by Boggs and Dorothy C. Lewis
    - Revisions and Corrections to Manual
    - Abridged Area Classification
    - General Plans
    - New Subjects for Manual, Miscellaneous
    - Material for Attention in Improving Manual
    - Manual
      - Typed Copy, 28 Apr. 1931, Annotated, Jan. 1932
      - Mimeographed
        - Jan. 1932
        - Jan. 1932, with Proposed Changes Insert, 4 Jan. 1935, (2 folders) (Box 14)
        - Apr. 1938, with Note, 10 Apr. 1945
        - Date Not Shown
    - "Department of State. Divisions of Publication, Geographic Section. Rules for Map Cataloguing" (2 copies)
    - Map Cataloging, Department of State
      - 1930-1931
      - 1943, on Samples, etc., for Explaining Technique
      - Area Classification, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Eumorphic Equal-Area Map Projection Formulas & Computations, 1927-1953
  - General Drafting Co., Inc., 1928-1930
  - Geographic and Mapping Projects for Unesco, 1947
  - "Geographic and Other Scientific Techniques for Political Science"
  - "Geographic Encyclopedia of the World," in English
  - Geographic Film Strips, 1946 (Box 16)
  - Geographic Projects for the American Council of Learned Societies, 1947-1949
  - Globes, 1953-1954
  - International Geographers' Union
  - "Inventory: The Earth and Its Tenants", (4 folders)
  - Journey of John R. Mott
    - re Maps for His Book, 1946-1947
    - Source Material for Maps, 1946-1947
  - "National Atlas of the United States" (Box 17)
    - Advisory Committee
    - Association of American Geographers Committee and Others, (2 folders)
    - Canadian, British, and Other National Atlases
    - Executive Committee
    - Miscellany
    - Roger Smith Conference, 8 June 1949
  - Nystrom (A. J.) & Co., Contract, 1927-1928
  - Possible Papers for Publication, Correspondence (Box 18)
  - "Regional Proverbial Wisdom"
  - "Savoy Free Zones"
  - Traffic Problems, 1939-1941
  - Warsaw Conference, 1934
  - Washington, D.C., and Vicinity, Road Map
    - 1929-1931
    - 1934, (2 folders)
  - Water Boundaries Articles, Correspondence, 1951
- Writings File, 1931-1954 (Box 19-23)
  Articles, books, and speeches.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Africa: Maps and Man" (Box 19)
  - "American Hemispheres"
  - "Apuntaciones Sobre los Aspectos Geograficos de un Plan Viable para el Arreglo de la Controversia Boliviano-Paraguaya de Limites"
  - Arts Club talk on maps, circa 1935, Notes
  - "Boundary Functions and the Principles of Boundary-Making"
  - "Centers: A Study in Social Unity"
  - "The Changing Significance of Geographic Locations"
  - "Comparative Distortion of Shape in Three Equal-Area Map Projections"
  - "Delimination of the Great Lakes Boundary"
  - "Geography and Its Relation to Political Science and Government"
  - "Geographic Aspects of European Emigration to the United States"
  - "The Geometry and Geography of Communications"
  - "Global Relations of the United States", (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - "Globe Manual"
  - International Boundaries, (2 folders); (6 folders) (Box 21, Box 22)
  - "Library Classification and Cataloging of Geographic Material"
  - "Mapping the Changing World"
  - "Notes on Map Making"
  - "Physiography of the Roof of Earth" (Box 23)
  - "A Plan for American Participation of Uninterrupted International Peace"
  - "Problems of Water-Boundary Definition"
  - "Seasonal Variations in Daylight, Twilight, and Darkness"
  - Speeches and Talks, 1945-1945, Notes
  - "Taking It for Granted," circa 1950, Notes
- Lectures, 1938-1942 (Box 23-24)
  Course notes of lecture series given at Columbia University.
  Arranged in numbered sequence as received from the donor, with a file of correspondence at the beginning and miscellany at the end.
  - Columbia University, 1939-1942
    - Boundaries
      - * Correspondence, 1938-1939
      - 1. What They Are and How They Function
      - 2. Classification and Terminology
      - 3. U.S.-Interstate, (2 folders)
      - 4. Latin America (Box 24)
      - 5. European Boundary Functions
      - 6. Europe
      - 7. Asia
      - 8. Africa
      - 9. Water
      - * International
      - * Miscellany
- Subject File, 1915-1954 (Box 25-30)
  Subject files related to professional interests, but of an avocational nature.
  - American Christian Literature Society for Moslems, Inc. (Box 25)
  - American Geographic Society
  - Berea College, Berea, Ky.
  - Boundaries
    - General, (3 folders)
    - Offshore Water Boundary Delimination
    - U.S., Canadian Boundary (Box 26)
    - U.S., Canadian Boundary Treaties
    - U.S., Mexico Boundary Treaties
  - Congo Constitution Committee, Correspondence, 1921-1923
  - Denoyer-Geppert Co., Scientific School Map Makers
  - Exhibitions, Art and Science Notes
  - Foreign Survey Department (Box 27)
  - Graphic Standards for Maps
  - Interchurch World Movement
  - Map Projections
  - Panama Protestant Missionary, Conference Material, (3 folders)
  - Regions of the World (Box 28)
    - Guide to Boggs's System
    - A World
      - Population
      - 000 General Information
      - 050 Geographical Publications
      - 100 Mathematical Geography
      - 115 Map Projections
      - 230 Climate, Meteorology, etc.
      - 700 Missionary Geography
      - 750 Geography's Debt to Missions
      - 801 History of Religions
      - 811 Christian Missions, Administrative Problems
      - 812 Missionary Surveys
      - 865 Mohammedanism
    - Ab Pacific Basin
      - 000 General Information
    - B Eastern Hemisphere
      - 801 History of Religions
    - Bn Near East
      - 840 Map of Protestant Missions, 1920, Data Used in Compiling Same
    - Bt Turkey (Europe and Asia)
      - 000 General Information
    - Ca Latin America (Box 29)
      - 840 Panama Congress, Feb. 1916
      - 840 Protestant Missions
      - 840 Protestant Missions, "Berea in Latin America"
    - D Africa
      - 412 Boundaries
      - 547 Railroads
    - Dgb Egypt
      - 000 General Information
    - E Asia
      - 000 General Information
    - Ecb Armenia
      - 000 General Information
    - Ej India
      - 000 General Information
    - En Near East (Asiatic)
      - 151 Distribution of Population, Geographic Factors
    - Es Siberia
      - 000 General Information
    - Ga Austria
      - 000 General Information
    - Gd Czechoslovakia
      - 000 General Information
    - Gf Finland
      - 000 General Information
    - Gh Germany
      - 000 General Information
    - Ghms Germany (Upper Silesia)
      - 000 General Information
    - Gi Greece
      - 000 General Information
    - Gj Hungary
      - 000 General Information
    - Gk Italy
      - 000 General Information
    - Gl Jugoslavia
      - 000 General Information
    - Go Poland
      - 000 General Information
    - Gwb Baltic Republics
      - 000 General Information
    - Gxc Albania
      - 000 General Information
    - Hm Mexico (Box 30)
      - 000 General Information
        - 840 Protestant Missions
    - Ho Central America
      - 840 Regional Conference, Mar. 1920
        - General
        - Records and Minutes
    - Kg Greenland
      - 000 General Information
      - Miscellany
- Miscellany, 1912-1945 (Box 31)
  Charts and maps, photographs, biographical material, printed matter, and notes.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Biographical File (Box 31)
  - Charts and Maps, 1932-1945, undated See also Oversize
  - General
  - Geography and Political Relations Course, Notes, circa 1948
  - M.A. Thesis, Notes, 1923-1924
  - Notebook, Undergraduate Course: Experimental Psychology, 1912-1913
  - Photographs
  - Printed Matter
- Oversize, 1932 (Box OV 1)
  Charts and maps.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Charts and Maps, 1932, undated (Container 31)